Well, if Mexico thought the US wasn't
going to manifest its destiny all over
them during this period, well,
they were wrong. That's right, it's time
to talk about the Mexican-American War.
So, if you're ready to get them brain
cows milked, let's get to it. Okay, so
as I talked about in the last video,
this time period in US history is
positively dominated by US westward
expansion, thanks in large part to the
hypnotic spell cast by the Manifest
Destiny ideology. And so, early in the
period, the pangs in the American belly
to expand west are going to cause the
Mexican-American War. So, let's talk
about how that happened. Now, James K.
Polk became president in 1844, and his
central campaign issue was US
expansionism. To that end, Polk aimed to
use his presidency to accomplish three
things: annex Texas, which the US had
been trying to do since the 1820s on
account of it was a fine place to expand
the cotton cultivation that was fueling
American industrialization. Also, Polk
aimed to settle the dispute with Great
Britain over Oregon and purchase
California from Mexico. So, in order to
acquire California, Polk sent a delegate
to the Mexican government with
authorization to purchase the territory
for $15 million, but the Mexican
officials went ahead and shut that
delegation all the way down. To quote
the Mexican government in Spanish, they
said, "No." Which, when being translated
into English, roughly means "No." But
why would the Mexican government turn
down a $15 million bag to keep
California when it wasn't all that
populated to begin with? Well, that's
because the Mexicans were still pretty
saucy about Texas. Oh, and by the way,
if you want note guides to follow along
with this video and all of my videos,
check the link in the description. Now,
recall that Texas was formerly Mexican
territory, and the Mexican government
had invited American migrants to settle
there and make a life under Mexican
authority, not least because they hoped
that those Americans would create a
buffer against powerful indigenous
groups like the Comanche, who had been
giving them trouble for years. But, long
story short, Americans living in Texas
launched a revolution against Mexico and
became an independent republic in 1836.
And for 10 years, that is how Texas
remained, not a part of Mexico and not a
part of the United States. And the
reason the US didn't go ahead and annex
Texas is because such an act would for
sure start a war with Mexico because the
Mexican government still claimed
ownership over the rebellious northern
territory. And perhaps even more
important, Whigs and other abolitionists
got whipped up into a proper fury over
the prospect of adding another slave
state Union. But, James K. Polk won the
presidency on the promise that he would
annex Texas, and so in 1845, that's
exactly what Congress did. And to Polk's
great disappointment, the war just
wasn't getting started soon enough, so
he decided to manufacture a start to the
conflict. Now, of special importance was
the dispute over the western border of
Texas. Texans claimed it was the Rio
Grande, while Mexicans claimed it was
the Nueces River. Therefore, upon being
snubbed regarding the purchase of
California, Polk sent American troops
led by General Zachary Taylor across the
Nueces River, and Mexico sent troops
across the Rio Grande to meet them.
fighting erupted in 1846, and Polk used
that opportunity to ask Congress for a
declaration of war against Mexico. His
justification was that American blood
had been spilled on American soil. To be
absolutely clear, that patch of land was
highly disputed, and it was no way
clearly American soil. But that didn't
matter much to Congress, who, after
drinking deeply from the cup of Manifest
Destiny, granted a declaration of war.
However, I should mention that this
declaration was granted over the loud
protest of anti-war Whigs who denounced
the war. And one of those sassy Whigs
was Abraham Lincoln, who demanded to
know the exact spot on which American
blood was spilled, which became known as
his spot resolution. But as I said, the
anti-war contingent got shut all the way
down, and the war was on. Now, you
really don't need to know how the war
was fought or any of the campaigns or
whatever. What you really need to know
are the effects of the war. So, let's
talk about it. Okay, so the
Mexican-American War ended in 1848 with
the signing of the Treaty of Guadalupe
Hidalgo, which had three major effects
that you're going to need to tuck away
in your brainfold. First, the Mexican
Cession granted the US over half of
Mexico's territory, which was the
largest land acquisition in US history,
second only to the Louisiana Purchase.
So, the treaty granted the US the
disputed territory in Texas and
established the border at the Rio
Grande. Additionally, the US gained the
New Mexico territory and California in
exchange for $15 million. And remember,
that was the price that Polk offered
Mexico for California alone, and now
it's all of this. So, from the
perspective of Manifest Destiny, the
Mexican-American War was a massive
success since the grand American empire
was now rubbing shoulders with both the
Atlantic and the Pacific oceans. Okay,
the second big effect of gaining all
this western land was a bitter dispute
over the expansion of slavery. So, even
before the war was over, this
congressional battle erupted with the
introduction of the Wilmot Proviso in
1846. So, what happened is that
Pennsylvania Congressman David Wilmot
added a rider to a funding bill that
mandated slavery be banned in all land
gained from the war with Mexico. And
even though it was voted down, this move
felt like a proper smack in the face to
southern representatives who wanted
those lands to expand slavery in order
to protect their own interests in the
government. Now, these slavery-loving
southern Democrats had a range of
reactions to the Treaty of Guadalupe
Hidalgo. Some opposed it because they
felt like it didn't go far enough. Like,
since the expansion of slavery was vital
to their survival and the securing of
political power, why not take all of
Mexico and expand the institution as far
south as they could? But others, like
John C. Calhoun, struggled with the
racial implications of the Mexican
Cession. Now, for sure, he was a slave
power man through and through and wanted
the institution to spread as far and
wide as possible. However, he worried
about the Mexicans and American Indians
who already populated those lands that
would be gained in the victory. And I
don't mean he worried about them and
their safety or any nonsense like that.
No, Calhoun believed the United States
to be the domain of white men, and
therefore he could not abide the thought
of offering citizenship to the many
Mexicans who lived in those lands.
Anyway, the point is, from the
perspective of American power and
Manifest Destiny, the lands gained in
the Mexican Cession were all blessing,
full stop. But from the perspective of
the expansion of slavery, the battle is
soon going to become so bitter and
divisive that the slaveholding states
would decide to leave the Union and form
their own country where slavery would
not be messed with. And then the third
big effect of the war was conflict with
Mexicans and American Indians. Now,
despite the abundant rhetoric that
described the western territories as
open and unpopulated, the lands of the
Mexican Cession were, uh, very much
populated. And once the territory
changed hands from Mexico to the United
States, conflicts erupted quick, fast,
and in a hurry. As for American Indians,
by far the most persistent threat was
the Comanche Nation. They had been
harassing settlers in Texas and northern
Mexico even before the territory changed
hands to the United States. In fact,
since the Comanche regularly attacked
and raided Mexican settlements in the
north and undermined their economy, US
expansionists argued that taking the
land and taming the Comanche was in fact
a noble and charitable act on behalf of
the Mexicans living there. But once the
territory belonged to the US, American
troops fought a series of conflicts with
the Comanche and Kiowa that lasted until
the 1870s, when the indigenous groups
had finally been conquered by American
military power, as well as ravaging
diseases they acquired from
westward-migrating Americans. But
Americans also had conflicts with
Mexicans who now lived under the
authority of the United States. Now,
during the Texas Revolution, white
American settlers known as Anglos fought
alongside Mexican natives known as
Tejanos. However, after independence was
achieved and Texas became the 28th state
to join the United States, the
relationship between the two groups
grew, uh, tense. First of all, the
Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo stated that
all former Mexican citizens in the
Mexican Cession would become US
citizens. However, states were able to
make their own citizenship laws, and in
no time they banned everyone except
white Mexican men from citizenship.
Second of all, Anglos, always hungry for
new soil, expelled many Tejanos from
their land and made further efforts to
marginalize their standing in Texas
society. For example, Texans pressured
Tejanos to assimilate to white American
culture, and some did submit by sending
their children to American schools and
attempting to convert them to
Protestantism. And for the most part,
such efforts failed, and Tejanos were
largely reduced to unskilled
agricultural laborers as Anglos took
dominion over their new state. However,
at least one Tejano resisted such
policies with violence, namely Juan
Cortina. Now, he was a wealthy Mexican
landowner who held territory on both
sides of the Rio Grande. When Texans
began claiming land on the American side
of the border for themselves, it
launched a series of conflicts known as
the Cortina Wars aimed at resisting
American expansion. And US forces, along
with the Texas Rangers, eventually
defeated Cortina and confined him to the
Mexican side of the Rio Grande. However,
from there Cortina continued to launch
intermittent raids against southern
Texas over the course of several
decades. So, all in all, the
Mexican-American War increased US
military prestige while at the same time
reigniting debates over the expansion of
slavery, and those debates are only
going to get more fiery over the next
few videos. Okay, you can click here to
watch my other videos from Minute Five,
or you can click here to get my video
note guides, which is going to help you
get all the contents of this course
firmly crammed into your brainfold. I'm
glad you came around, and I'll catch you
on the flip-flop. I'm ler out.